Guide to the Josef Albers Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Josef Albers papers
1899-1973
MS 32
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
13
(30 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, subject files, printed material, and family memorabilia, which document the personal life and professional career of Josef Albers. The papers contain some material relating to the Bauhaus school but the bulk of the material dates from Albers's arrival in the United States. The largest part of the papers is composed of published material by or about Albers or which contain reproductions of his work.
Albers, Josef, 1888-1976
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Josef Albers, 1960, and transfer from the Art and Architecture Library, 1985 and 1989.
Scope and Contents
The Josef Albers Papers consist of correspondence, subject files, printed material, and family memorabilia, which document the personal life and professional career of Josef Albers. The earliest material in the papers reflects Albers family history and his work at the Bauhaus in Germany. The bulk of the material, however, dates from Albers arrival in the United States to teach at Black Mountain College. The largest part of the papers is composed of books, magazines, clippings, and exhibition catalogues, which are either about Albers or which contain his writings or reproductions of his works.
Manuscripts and Archives received some of the papers from Josef Albers in 1960. Material which had been collected by the Art and Architecture Library was added to the papers in 1985. This material, in the form of bound folios of printed works by and about Albers, is arranged together with the materials received from Albers in five sections: Correspondence, Subject files, Exhibition catalogs and reproductions of Albers's work, Writings by Albers, and Memorabilia. Oversized material from these sections has been arranged at the end of the collection. Most of the material is in English but there are many items in German.
The correspondence in the papers, most of which is filed in the section Correspondence, is fragmentary and consists of only occasional exchanges with a number of personal friends. Only the correspondence with Hans and Sophie Arp, Willi Baumeister, Katherine S. Dreier, Lyonel Feininger, Walter Gropius, Wassily Kandinski, and Oskar Schlemmer is more extensive. Many of the letters in Correspondence concern arrangements for Albers's positions at Black Mountain College, Harvard University, and Yale University. A file of congratulatory letters on Albers's Yale appointment is included in the subject file "Yale University" and there is some correspondence relating to Albers's family history in folder 266. The subject file on the Bauhaus also includes correspondence and other documentation concerning Albers's affiliation with and departure from the school.
Subject files also include some material on the life and work of Albers's wife Anni Albers, printed material on Black Mountain College, and Albers's annual reports as head of the Department of Design to the president of Yale University. The vast majority of this section, however, consists of writings about Albers. These files include books, magazines, and newspaper articles in which Albers's life and work are described. These materials are arranged chronologically by publication date.
The two sections Exhibitions catalogs and reproductions of Albers's work and Writings by Albers are very similar in content, both containing printed copies of Albers's works and writings. The section of writings includes articles, poems, and books by Albers. An exhibition catalog or volume honoring Albers, which incorporates statements or poems by Albers's along with reproductions of his work might also be seen as a writing. Since the container listing does not provide an item by item listing for each catalog and article, the reader is cautioned to search both sections to locate specific published items. Each section is arranged chronologically by date of publication. Lists, which were created as contents lists to the portfolios transferred from the Art and Architecture Library, (folder 264) may be helpful in determining the variety and titles of material filed in the two sections.
In addition, the writings section includes draft copies for lectures, speeches, and other writings by Albers. Several of these relate to Black Mountain College and include remarks at Black Mountain College luncheons in New York City and copy for the Black Mountain College catalogs. Printed copies of these catalogs are in the subject files. The exhibitions section includes photographs of some exhibits and announcements and other publicity for exhibits, even if there is no catalog for the exhibit in the file. The files of reproductions of Albers's work include printed copies of Albers's work used in a variety of ways. These include a geometry textbook using a painting as an illustration, a museum appointment calendar of works by several artists, publicity for the sale of Albers's work which includes facsimile reproductions, and the Alberses' Christmas cards (folder 166).
Memorabilia includes citations and awards which Albers received, personal photographs, and family papers. The personal papers document Albers's family in Germany and include copies of several official documents relating to births, deaths, and marriages.
Biographical / Historical
Josef Albers was born in Bottrop, Germany, on March 19, 1888. He studied art in schools in Berlin, Essen, and Munich before joining the Bauhaus school in 1920. From the completion of his studies in 1923 until the school was closed by the Nazis in 1933, Albers remained at the Bauhaus as a teacher. In 1933 Albers joined the faculty of Black Mountain College in North Carolina, where he remained until 1950 when he accepted an appointment as chairman of the Yale University Department of Design. He retired in 1958 and died on March 25, 1976.
Conditions Governing Access
Box 26 must be used under the supervision of a reference archivist.
Art, Modern -- 20th Century; Artists -- United States; Exhibit catalogs; Painters; Albers, Anni, 1899-1994; Albers, Josef, 1888-1976; Arp, Jean, 1887-1966; Baumeister, Willi, 1889-1955; Dreier, Katherine S. (Katherine Sophie), 1877-1952; Feininger, Lyonel, 1871-1956; Gropius, Walter, 1883-1969; Kandinsky, Wassily, 1866-1944; Schlemmer, Oskar, 1888-1943; Taeuber-Arp, Sophie, 1889-1943; Bauhaus; Black Mountain College (Black Mountain, N.C.); Harvard University. Graduate School of Design; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. School of Art and Architecture
- Inventory
  - Correspondence
    - Arp, Hans Jean & Sophie Tauber-Arp, 1933-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Barr, Alfred H. Jr., 1929, 1933, 1937, 1950, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Baumeister, Willi, 1934-1948 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Bennington College, 1934, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - de Kooning, Willem, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Dreier, Katherine S., 1936-1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Dreier, Theodore, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Feild, Robert D., 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Feininger, Lyonel, 1934-1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Gropius, Walter and family, 1921-1958, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Harvard University. Graduate School of Design, 1936-1942 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      General
      See also: box 1, folder 8
    - Hayes, Roland, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Howe, George, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Jawlensky, Alexej von, 1941, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Johnson, Philip, 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Kandinsky, Wassily and N____, 1934-1940, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Klee, Paul, 1936-1940 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Kline, Franz, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Lippold, Richard, 1952, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Marcks, Gerhard, 1934, 1950, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Mérida, Carlos, 1924, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Moholy-Nagy, Lászlo, 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Mondrian, Piet, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Muche, George, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Ozenfant, Amédée, 1941, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Papadaki, Stamo, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Schlemmer, Oskar, 1934-1938 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Schwitters, Kurt & Helma, 1935-1937 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Schlemmer, Tut, 1950-1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Wilder, Thornton, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Winter, Fritz, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Yale University, 1948-1959 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Miscellaneous, 1933-1969, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Subject files
    - Albers, Anni, 1946-1963 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      See also: box 29
    - Bauhaus, 1923-1939, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 30-33)
    - Black Mountain College, 1935-1948, undated (Box 3, Folder 34-37)
      See also: box 1, folder 7
    - Writings about Albers
      - Alphabetized personal comments, 1934-1958, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - Books and magazines, 1928-1936 (Box 3, Folder 39-40)
      - Books and magazines, 1937-1950 (Box 4, Folder 41-48)
      - Books and magazines, 1951-1956 (Box 5, Folder 49-57)
      - Books and magazines, 1956-1957 (Box 6, Folder 58-61)
      - Books and magazines, 1958-1960 (Box 7, Folder 62-68)
      - Books and magazines, 1960-1962 (Box 8, Folder 69-75)
      - Books and magazines, 1963-1967 (Box 9, Folder 76-84)
      - Books and magazines, 1968-1971, n. d. (Box 10, Folder 85-91)
      - Newspaper articles, 1933-1948 (Box 10, Folder 92-95)
      - Newspaper articles, 1949-1965, n. d. (Box 11, Folder 96-103)
    - Yale University, 1948-1958 (Box 11, Folder 104-105)
  - Exhibition catalogs and reproductions of Albers's work
    See also: Box 29
    - Catalogues and pamphlets, 1932-1953 April 12 (Box 12, Folder 106-113)
    - Catalogues and pamphlets, 1953 April 13-1957 June 15 (Box 13, Folder 114-120)
    - Catalogues and pamphlets, 1957 June 16-1959 (Box 14, Folder 121-127)
    - Catalogues and pamphlets, 1960 (Box 15, Folder 128-132)
    - Catalogues and pamphlets, 1961 January-1962 January 7 (Box 16, Folder 133-138)
    - Catalogues and pamphlets, 1962 January-1963 March (Box 17, Folder 139-144)
    - Catalogues and pamphlets, 1963 April-1967 (Box 18, Folder 145-155)
    - Catalogues and pamphlets, 1968-1973, undated (Box 19, Folder 156-160)
    - Photographs of exhibitions, 1934-1957 (Box 20, Folder 161)
    - Reproductions of Albers's work, 1934-1951 (Box 20, Folder 162-167)
    - Reproductions of Albers's work, 1952-1969, undated (Box 21, Folder 168-191)
  - Writings by Albers
    - Articles and interviews by Albers, 1935-1946, 1952-1958 (Box 22, Folder 192-209)
    - Articles and interviews by Albers, 1958-1961 (Box 23, Folder 210-224)
    - Articles and interviews by Albers, 1961-1962 (Box 24, Folder 225-236)
    - Articles and interviews by Albers, 1963-1969, undated (Box 25, Folder 237-249)
      See also: box 29, folder 275
    - Books
      - Homage to the Square
        See: box 30
      - Interaction of Color, 1963 (Box 26)
        Conditions Governing Access
        Interaction of Color must be used under the supervision of Manuscripts and Archives staff.
      - Interviews with Albers, 1965-1967
        See: Historical Sound Recordings
    - Lectures and speeches, 1928-1946 (Box 27, Folder 250-262)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 27, Folder 263)
  - Memorabilia
    - Bibliographic data, 1928-1968, undated (Box 28, Folder 264)
    - Citations and awards, 1932-1962, undated (Box 28, Folder 265)
      See also: box 29, folder 271
    - Personal papers, 1899-1949 (Box 28, Folder 266)
    - Photographs, including passports, 1930, 1935, 1961 (Box 28, Folder 267)
    - Publicity, 1944, 1959-1966, undated (Box 28, Folder 268)
    - Miscellanea, 1953, 1961-1963, undated (Box 28, Folder 269)
  - Oversized material
    - Anni Albers scrapbook, 1943-1973 (Box 29, Folder 270)
    - Citations and awards, 1931-1959 (Box 29, Folder 271)
    - Reproductions of Albers' work, 1960, undated (Box 29, Folder 272-273)
    - Writings about Albers, 1962, 1964, 1969, undated (Box 29, Folder 274)
    - Writings by Albers, 1968, undated (Box 29, Folder 275)
    - Miscellanea, 1940 (Box 29, Folder 276)
    - Homage to the Square, 1962 (Box 30)